Louise Guillouët

Development and environmental economist +1 9293096583 | +33 614646883 louise.guillouet@columbia.edu | louiseguillouet.com

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

Young professional committed to international development: six years of experience in award-winning development and environmental economics research, policy analysis and the private sector

Demonstrated communication and leadership skills: leading multicultural teams in the field and at headquarters in research, private-sector, policy and educational projects

Work experience in emerging markets: French Polynesia, Colombia, China, Myanmar, Burkina Faso Languages: French (Native), English (Fluent), Spanish (Proficient), Chinese (Beginner)

EDUCATION

Columbia University

Expected 2022

Ph.D. in Economics

New York, NY

- Dissertation: "The Welfare Effects of New Firms and New Goods in Developed and Developing Countries"
- Recipient of Oxford University's Global Priorities Institute Fellowship (2021)
- Recipient of Columbia University's Dissertation Fellowship (2021), Wueller Fellowship for best predissertation proposal (2020), Alliance Fellowship (2019), Dean's Fellowship (2016)

Paris School of Economics

2016

M.Sc. Analysis and Policy in Economics Summa Cum Laude

Paris, France

- Dissertation: "Action of Precaution: A New Interpretation of the Precautionary Principle"
- Recipient of the American Foundation for the Paris School of Economics International Fellowship (2016)

Sciences Po and Université Pierre et Marie Curie

2013

B.A. and B.Sc. Cum Laude in Science and Social Science

Paris, France

WORK EXPERIENCE

Columbia University

2017 - present

Researcher in Development Economics

New York, NY - Yangon, Myanmar - Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso

- · Coordinate up to eight simultaneous research projects with researchers spread over three continents
- Organize and conduct interviews with private stakeholders and policymakers in Myanmar and Burkina Faso
- Design, pilot and supervise the implementation of eight surveys in Myanmar and Burkina Faso
- · Adapt field work to the safety conditions required by the COVID-19 pandemic using telephone and Internet
- Organize and present at private-sector and policy outreach events with more than 100 people in Myanmar
- Write several successful grant proposals detailed below, raising over \$250,000
- Present at internal seminars and academic and policy conferences detailed below

Teaching Assistant in Economics

2017 - 2020

- Taught principles of economics, intermediate macroeconomics, economic development and industrial organization to groups of 5 to 30 elite undergraduate students coming from dozens of different countries
- Adapted to different styles of teaching, in-person and online. Average evaluation given by students: 4.3/5

Research Assistant in Environmental Economics

Summer 2017

- Create extensions for a theoretical model of the welfare effects of corrective policies
- Wrote code to check the robustness of the empirical analysis of an energy-saving program
- Reviewed the manuscript before the successful resubmission: Costa, Francisco, and François Gerard. "Hysteresis and the welfare effect of corrective policies: Theory and evidence from an energy-saving program." Journal of Political Economy 129.6 (2021): 1705-1743.

ENGIE - Strategy department

March 2015 – August 2015

Strategy analyst Paris, France

• Researched topics such as the future of gas, customer-centricity and franchising in the context of the company's shift from a fossil fuel major to a leader of the energy and environmental transition

• Wrote reports for the board of directors of the company and other stakeholders of the global energy industry

NERA Economic Consulting - Environment, Energy and Networks

September 2014 – February 2015

Economic analyst

Paris, France

- Quantified the economic impact of the EU Emissions Trading System on the local and global cement industry and proposed policy adjustments
- Valued the high-stake, high-uncertainty acquisition of a rare gas tract
- Designed presentations and presented to clients up to the board of directors

French Treasury - Regional Economic Service in China

June 2014 - August 2015

Research officer

Shanghai, China

- Conducted a study and wrote a report about regional and national policies supporting innovation
- · Organized and conducted interviews with dozens of private-sector leaders and policymakers

Paris School of Economics

February 2014 - May 2014

Research Assistant in African Economic History

Paris, France

- Designed a search strategy to retrieve new information from the French National Archives about historical income distribution in the former French colonies
- Created a unique dataset which lead to a publication: Alvaredo, Facundo, Denis Cogneau, and Thomas Piketty. "Income inequality under colonial rule evidence from French Algeria, Cameroon, Tunisia, and Vietnam and comparisons with British colonies 1920–1960." Journal of Development Economics (2021): 102680.

AIESEC June 2013 – July 2013

Project Officer

Cartagena, Colombia

- Organized a team of 10 people from different countries to organize engaging events for students
- Engaged with leaders of a local Colombian school to improve management practices and raise funds

Progressive Policy Institute

January 2013 – May 2013

Policy Analyst

Washington, DC

- Analyzed health and environmental policy proposals under discussions at the U.S. Congress
- Wrote notes and presentations for private-sector stakeholders and policymakers

RESEARCH PAPERS

The Demand Side of Firm Growth: Evidence from Mexico

- Analyze big data to identify the barriers that prevent Mexican firms from introducing new goods
- Design a model of consumer learning under uncertainty, suggesting transparency policies could contribute to private-sector growth and local job creation

Language Barriers in Multinationals and Knowledge Transfers

Submitted

with Amit Khandelwal, Rocco Macchiavello and Matthieu Teachout

- Design a model of multinationals' organization to explain the low level of on-the-job training
- Test the model in two experimental protocols, including a Randomized Controlled Trial where we randomly offered a free English training to half of 298 employees working for foreign firms in Myanmar
- Evaluate the benefit of a policy subsidizing language training in generating human capital growth

Precaution, Information and Time-inconsistency: On the Value of the Precautionary Principle with David Martimort

- Design a model describing technologies that are profitable economically but pose environmental threats
- Compute the optimal policy paths depending on the regulator's ability to commit

The Unequal Gains from Entry at the Top: Estimating the Whole Foods Effect

- · Analyze big data to estimate the causal effect of gentrification on low-income residents' welfare
- Design a model to think about what policy actions could mitigate these negative impacts

RESEARCH GRANTS

Supply-Chain Linkages with FDI Firms: Experimental Evidence from Myanmar (£175,394) International Growth Centre (IGC), with Amit Khandelwal and Rocco Macchiavello - returned	2020
Evaluating a novel approach for expanding the pool of entrepreneurs in Myanmar (£19,774) IGC's Small and Growing Business Fund, with Réka Zempléni - returned	2020
Government Relief Measures for Small and Medium Enterprises (SME) in Burkina Faso (£31,828 Private-Enterprise Development in Low-Income Countries (PEDL), with Josh Deutschmann, Soumaïla Gansonré and Aristide S. Ouédraogo	3) 2020
The Social Quality of Goods (\$25,000) National Science Foundation Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant	2020
SELECTED CONFERENCES AND PRESENTATIONS	
Allied Social Science Association Annual Meeting (online)	2022
CEPR's Structural Transformation and Economic Growth, Centre for the Study of African Economic Society for Institutional and Organizational Economics, Oxford GPI (all online)	es 2021
CEPR/EBRD's Economics of Transition Seminar, Northeastern Universities Development Consortium, Empirical Management Conference (all online)	2020
French Association of Environmental and Resource Economics Annual Conference, Sciences Po Paris Friday Seminar (France), University of Warwick Economics PhD Conference (UK)	2019
World Congress of Environmental and Resource Economics (Sweden), Innovation for Poverty Action SME Meeting (USA), PEDL Workshop on the Frontiers of Research (EAU)	2018
OTHER SKILLS	

Computer Languages: Microsoft Office, Stata, R, Python (including geopandas), MATLAB, Mathematica, Latex **Human Languages**: French (Native), English (Fluent), Spanish (Proficient), Chinese (Beginner)